When I saw a piece of technology called Kinect --
عندما رأيت نطاق " كينيكت "
it was called Natal -- I was inspired,
كان يدعى حينها " ناتال " لقد أُلهمت
and I thought for a moment,
حينها لوهلة
maybe it's possible
انه قد يمكن
to address that one problem of storytelling,
ان نتخلص من فكرة السرد في الالعاب
to create a character
لكي نخرج بشخصية
which seemed alive,
تبدو حقيقة
which noticed me,
تميز اللاعب
that could look me in the eyes
ويمكنها النظر الى عينيه
and feel real,
وتبدو حقيقة فعلا
and sculpt a story about our relationship.
وتتشكل قصة تلك اللعبة بحسب علاقتنا معها
And so a year ago,
لذا منذ عام
I showed this off
قررت ان اعرض
at a computer show called E3.
شيئاً يدعى " إي 3 " - الذكاء المستوى الثالث -
And this was a piece of technology
وقد كان هذا جزء من تكنولوجيا
with someone called Claire interacting with this boy.
تدعى " كلير " وهي تكنولوجيا تواصل مع هذا الطفل
And there was a huge row online
وقد نتج عنها جدل كبير على الانترنت
about, "Hey, this can't be real."
ان ما عرضناه لا بد وان يكون خدعة ما
And so I waited till now
لذا انتظرت حتى اليوم
to have an actual demo
لكي اخرج بالعرض الحقيقي
of the real tech.
للتكنولوجيا التي اصبحت واقعا
Now, this tech incorporates
وتتضمن هذه التكنولوجيا 3 مكونات
three big elements.
اساسية
The first is a Kinect camera,
هي اولا كميرة تصوير من كينيكت
which will be out in November,
والتي سوف تدخل الاسواق في نوفمبر القادم
some incredible AI
وهي تحوي نظام فريد من الذكاء الإصطناعي
that was hidden in the dusty vaults,
والتي كانت مخبأة في الخزن القديمة
collecting dust
لميكروسوفت .. هكذا ندعو بعض المشاريع لدينا
in Microsoft,
" مخبأة في الخزن القديمة "
plus our quite crude
بالاضافة الى هوسنا الشديد للوصول
attempts at AI
الى الذكاء الإصطناعي
at a company called Lionhead,
بالتعاون مع شركة " رأس الاسد "
mixing all those things together
وبجمع هذه المكونات
just to get to this one simple idea:
وصلنا الى فكرة اساسية
to create a real, living
وهي صناعة كمبيوتر
being in a computer.
حقيقي و حي
Now, I'll be honest with you
ولكي اكون صادقاً معكم
and say that most of it
يمكن القول ان معظم ما يجري
is just a trick,
مبرمج على الحاسوب .. اي انه نوع من الخدع
but it's a trick that actually works.
ولكنها خدعة تبدو حقيقية
So why don't we go over and have
حسنا دعونا من هذا .. ولننظر الى النموذج
a look at the demo now.
هذا هو العرض الذي اريد ان اريكم اياه
This is Dimitri.
هذا هو ديميتري
Dimitri, just waggle your arm around.
ديميرتي سوف يحرك يديه فقط
Now, you notice he's sitting.
وكما ترون فهو جالس فحسب
There are no controllers,
ولايوجد اي اجهزة تحكم
no keyboards,
ولا لوحات مفاتيح
or mice,
ولا ميكرفونات
or joysticks, or joypads.
او انماط تحكم
He is just going to use
فهو سوف يستخدم فحسب
his hand, his body and his voice,
يديه وجسده وصوته
just like humans interact with their hands, body and voice.
كما يتفاعل الانسان الحقيقي .. بيديه ..وجسده ..وصوته
So let's move forward.
حسناً لننطلق
You're going to meet Milo for the first time.
سوف تقابلون " مايلو " للمرة الاولى هنا
We had to give him a problem
وكان يتوجب علينا ان نصنع مشكلة ما
because when we first created Milo,
لانه عندما اخترعنا مايلو اول مرة
we realized that he came across as a little bit of a brat,
ادركنا انه سوف ينمو ليصبح طفل مزعج
to be honest with you.
وهذا الواقع ..
He was quite a know-it-all,
فقد كان يعرف كل شيء
and he wanted to kind of make you laugh.
وكان يريد ان يجعلك تضحك فحسب
So the problem we introduced to him was this:
لذا قمنا بصنع مشكلة له وهي كالتالي
he's just moved house.
لقد انتقل الى منزل جديد
He's moved from London
من لندن .. الى
to New England, over in America.
نيو انجلند .. في الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
His parents are too busy
ووالده مشغولان كثيرا
to listen to his problems,
لكي يستمعا الى مشاكله
and that's when he starts almost conjuring you up.
وهنا سوف يبدأ بالتعرف إليك - اللاعب -
So here he is
وها هو
walking through the grass.
يسير على الاعشاب
And you're able to interact with his world.
وسوف تكون قادرا على التفاعل مع عالمه
The cool thing is, what we're doing
واجمل شيء اننا قمنا
is we're changing the mind
اقصد .. ان دماغ مايلو يتغير
of Milo constantly.
بصورة مستمرة
That means no two people's Milos
اي يعني انه لن يوجد في العالم على الاطلاق شخصيتين
can be the same.
من مايلو متشابهتين
You're actually sculpting a human being here.
لانك تصنع شخصية انسان حقيقي هنا .. بفعل قراراتك
So, he's discovering the garden.
حسنا .. ها هو يكتشف الحديقة
You're helping him discover the garden
وسوف تساعده - كلاعب - ان يستكشف الحديقة
by just pointing out these snails.
وها هو يشير الى الحلزونات
Very simple at the start.
وهي بداية بسيطة للبدء
By the way, if you are a boy, it's snails;
بالمناسبة ان كان اللاعب ذكر .. فهي حلزونات
if you're a girl, it's butterflies
ان كان انثى .. فهي فراشات
because what we found was that girls hate snails.
لاننا اكتشفنا ان الفتيات يكرهن الحلزونات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So remember, this is the first time you've met him,
تذكروا .. هذه هي المرة الاولى التي تقابلون فيها مايلو
and we really want to draw you in and make you more curious.
ونحن نحاول فعلا ان نجعلك تصاب بالفضول لاكتشاف هذه الشخصية
His face, by the way,
بالمناسبة وجهه
is fully AI-driven.
مبرمج بالكامل عبر الذكاء الإصطناعي
We have complete control over his blush responses,
فلدينا تحكم كامل بخدوده
the diameter of his nostrils
وبقطر انفه
to denote stress.
لكي يعبر كل ذلك معا عن مدى توتره
We actually do something called body matching.
ولقد برمجنا شيء يدعى " محاكاة الجسد المقابل "
If you're leaning forward,
اي انك ان املت بجسدك الى الامام
he will try and slightly change
سوف ترى تغيراُ بسيطا
the neuro-linguistic nature of his face,
في طبيعة وجهه
because we went out with this strong idea:
لان هدفنا الرئيسي كان
how can we make you believe that something's real?
كيف نجعلك تصدق ان هذا الشخص حقيقي
Now we've used the hand.
الان يتم استخدم اليد ..
The other thing to use is your body.
والشيء الاخر الذي يمكن استخدامه هو جسد اللاعب
Why not just, instead of pushing left and right
بدلا من التحرك يمنة ويسرة بواسطة الفأرة
with a mouse or with a joypad,
او بواسطة اجهزة التحكم ..
why not use your body just to lean on the chair --
لان كل هذا يمكن الاستعاضة عنه بحركة جسدك الى الامام والخلف
again, relaxed?
مرة اخرى .. استرح
You can lean back,
يمكنك ان ترخي ظهرك الى الخلف
but the camera will change its perspective
وسوف تتاقلم الكميرا معك وتغير من منظروها
depending on which way you're looking.
كما انها سوف تتجاوب مع حركة عينيك
So Dimitri's now going to use --
الآن ديميتري سوف
he's used his hand; he's used his body.
يستخدم جسده .. ويديه
He's now going to use the other thing which is essential,
وسوف يستخدم امر هام جدا ومحوري
and that's his voice.
وهو صوته
Now, the thing about voice is,
الان .. ان مشكلة الصوت
our experience with voice recognition
بحكم خبرتنا .. كانت التعرف عليه
is pretty awful, isn't it?
لان هذه مشكلة عويصة .. اليس كذلك
It never works.
ولا تنجح عادة
You order an airline ticket; you end up in Timbuktu.
حيث تطلب تذكرة طيران بصوتك الى لندن .. لتجد نفسك في تيمباكو
So we've tackled that problem,
لذا عالجنا هذه المشكلة بصورة مباشرة
and we've come up with a solution, which we'll see in a second.
وقد قمنا بحل سوف ترونه خلال ثوان
Milo: I could just squish it.
مايلو : هل اسحقها
Peter Molyneux: What are you going to do, Dimitri?
بيتر مولينكس : مالذي سوف تقوم به يا ديميتري
Female Voice: Squashing a snail may not seem important,
صوت : ان سحق الحلزون لا يبدو امراً ضروريا
but remember, even this choice
ولكن تذكروا ان حتى هذا الخيار البسيط
will affect how Milo develops.
سوف يؤثر على نمو مايلو
Do you want Milo to squash it?
هل تريد ان يسحقها مايلو ؟
When you see the microphone,
عندما تجد اشارة الميكرفون
say ... (PM: Squash.) ... yes to decide.
قل " اسحق " اذا قررت ذلك
Dimitri: Go on, Milo. Squash it.
ديميتري : هيا مايلو . .اسحقه
PM: No. That's the wrong thing to do.
بيتر مولينكس : ربما هذا تصرفٌ خاطىء
Now look at his response.
الان انظروا الى ردة فعل مايلو
He said, "Go on, Milo. Squash it."
لقد قال " هيا اسحقه "
What we're using there is,
ان ما نستخدمه هنا
we're using something, a piece of technology called Tellme.
هو شيء تكنولوجي يدعى " تيلمي "
It's a company that Microsoft acquired some years ago.
وهي تابعة لميكروسوفت انشئت منذ عدة سنوات
We've got a database of words which we recognize.
ولدينا كلمات كثيرة يمكن تميزها
We pick those words out.
ونحن نختار هذه الكلمات ونبرمجها
We also reference that
كما اننا نقوم بارشفة
with the tonation database
الكلمات الى مركز معلومات مايلو
that we build up of Dimitri's voice,
والذي ينمو تبعا لصوت ديميتري
or the user's voice.
او صوت اللاعب
Now we need to have a bit more engagement,
والان سوف نتفاعل اكثر
and again, what we can do
ومرة اخرى الذي يمكن القيام به
is we can look at the body.
هو التفاعل مع الجسد
And we'll do that in a second.
وسوف نقوم بذلك الان
Milo: I wonder how deep it is.
مايلو : اتسائل كم عمق هذه البحيرة
Deep.
عميقة ربما
PM: Okay. So what we're going to do now
بيتر مولينكس : حسنا ان الذي سنقوم به الان هو
is teach Milo to skim stones.
تعليمه كيفية تعويم الحصى
We're actually teaching him.
وسوف نعلمه حقاً ذلك
It's very, very interesting
وهو امرٌ ممتع جدا
that men, more than women,
للرجال اكثر منه للنساء
tend to be more competitive here.
لانهم تنافسيون اكثر
They're fine with teaching Milo for the first few throws,
وسوف يجدون انه من المناسب تعليم مايلو في الرميات الاولى
but then they want to beat Milo,
ولكن وبعد عدة رميات نجد ميلاً لديهم لغلبه والتفوق عليه
where women,
بينما النساء
they're more nurturing about this.
يبدو الامر بالنسبة لهم تربويٌ أكثر
Okay, this is skimming stones.
حسناً هذا هو تعويم الاحجار
How do you skim stones?
كيف يمكننا تعويم الحجر
You stand up,
نحن نقف
and you skim the stone.
ومن ثم نرمي الحجر على سطح الماء
It's that simple.
ان الامر بهذه البساطة
Just recognizing your body,
فقط راقب حركة جسدك
recognizing the body's motions, the tech,
وسوف تراقب التكنولوجيا تلك الحركة
understanding that you've gone
وسوف تستقبلها وتدخلها الى الحاسوب
from sitting down to standing up.
من بداية وقوفك الى جلوسك
Again, all of this is done
ومرة اخرى كل هذا صمم
in the way us humans do things,
لكي يتحاكي مع الافعال الحقيقية للبشر
and that's crucially important
وكان هذا ضروري جدا
if we want Milo to appear real.
لكي يبدو مايلو حقيقيٌ جداً
Female Voice: See if you can inspire him to do any better.
صوت : حاول ان تعلمه الرمي بصورة افضل
Try hitting the boat.
حاول ان تصيب القارب
Milo: Ahhh. So close.
مايلو : قريبة جداً
PM: That's Dimitri at his most competitive.
بيتر مولينكس : ها هو ديميتري يدخل المنافسة الان
Now beaten an 11-year-old child. Well done.
ويريد هزيمة طفل عمره 11 عام .. احسنت
Milo: Okay.
مايلو : حسناً
PM: So, Milo's being called back in by his parents,
بيتر مولينكس : هنا مايلو .. يتم مناداته من قبل والديه
giving us time to be alone
وهذا الوقت نتصرف به وحدنا بدون وجود مايلو
and to help him out.
لكي نساعده قليلا
Basically -- the bit that we missed at the start --
في الاساس لقد قمنا بتوسيخ الغرفة قليلا
his parents had asked him to clean up his room.
وقد طلب منه والده تنظيف الغرفة
And we're going to help him with this now.
وسوف نساعده في هذا هنا
But this is going to be an introduction,
وسوف يكون هنالك توجيه للطفل
and this is all about the deep psychology that we're trying to use.
وكل هذا ينطوي ضمن السيكلوجية التربوية للطفل
We're trying to introduce you
التي نحاول برمجتها فيه عبر افعال اللاعب
to what I believe is the most wonderful part,
والذي اعتقد ان هذا هو الجزء الاكثر روعة في هذه التكنولوجيا
you being able to talk
اي القدرة على التحدث
in your natural voice to Milo.
بصوتك الحقيقي الى مايلو
Now, to do that, we needed a set up,
الان نريد ان نرتب الامور هنا
like a magician's trick.
مثل السحر تغدو الغرفة نظيفة
And what we did was,
والذي قمنا به هو اننا وضعنا
we needed to give Milo this big problem.
مايلو في مأزق محرج
So as Dimitri
وسوف يقوم ديميتري
starts tidying up,
بترتيب الغرفة
you can overhear a conversation
وسوف يستمع الى المحادثة
that Milo's having with his parents.
التي تجري بين مايلو وبين والديه
Milo's Mom: Oh, you've got gravy all over the floor. (Milo: I didn't mean to!)
والدة مايلو : لقد اتسخت الارضية تماما .. ( مايو : لم اقصد هذا )
Milo's Mom: That carpet is brand new.
والدة مايلو : ان السجادة جديدة .. ولقد اتسخت الان
PM: So he's just spilled
بيتر مولينكس : حسنا لقد قام مايلو
a plate of sausages on the floor,
بايقاع طبق من النقانق على الارضية
on the brand-new carpet.
وتحديدا على السجادة الجديدة
We've all done it as parents; we've all done it as children.
وقد نتعرض جميعنا لهذا .. سواء كنا كباراُ او صغاراً
Now's a chance for Dimitri
وهذه هي الفرصة لكي يتصرف ديميتري
to kind of reassure and calm Milo down.
بنحو يهدىء ويقلل من توتر مايلو
It's all been too much for him.
فقد كان الضغط عليه كبيرة في الآونة الاخيرة
He's just moved house. He's got no friends.
فقد انتقل الى منزل جديد .. ولا يملك اي رفاق جدد
Now is the time
وهذه هو الوقت الذي تصبح فيه اللعبة
when we open that portal
مفتوحة المصاريع
and allow you to talk to Milo.
وسوف يتمكن اللاعب من التحدث الى مايلو
Female Voice: Why don't you try saying something encouraging
صوت : حاول ان تحمس مايلو
to cheer Milo up.
وان تجعله اكثر فرحاً
Dimitri: Come on, Milo. You know what parents are like.
ديميتري : هيا مايلو .. انت تعلم كيف هن الامهات
They're always getting stressed.
يغضبون دوما
Milo: What do they want to come here for anyway?
مايلو: لماذا قرروا الانتقال الى هنا
We don't know anyone.
نحن لا نعلم اي احد هنا
Dimitri: Well, you've got a new school to go to.
ديميتري : لديك مدرسة جديدة ستذهب اليها
You're going to meet loads of cool, new friends.
وسوف تقابل العديد من الاصدقاء الرائعين هناك
Milo: I just really miss my old house, that's all.
مايلو : ولكني احب منزلي القديم.. هذا كل مافي الامر
Dimitri: Well, this is a pretty awesome house, Milo.
ديميتري : حسنا .. وهذا منزل رائع ايضا . .. يا مايلو
You've got a cool garden to play in and a pond.
لديك حديقة يمكنك اللعب بها و استكشافها
Milo: It was good skimming stones.
مايلو : لقد احببت تعويم الاحجار
This looks nice.
يا له من امر رائع
You cleaned up my room.
لقد نظفت الغرفة
Thanks.
شكرا لك
PM: So after three-quarters of an hour,
بيتر مولينكس : حسناً بعد ثلاثة ارباع الساعة سيبدأ مايلو
he recognizes you.
بالتعرف اليك
And I promise you, if you're sitting in front of this screen,
وانا واثق ان كنت جالس الان امام الشاشة سوف
that is a truly wonderful moment.
تشعر شعوراً رائعا
And we're ready now
ونحن الان مستعدون
to tell a story about his childhood and his life,
لكي نتدخل في خضم طفولته وفي حياته
and it goes on,
وكل شي سيسير من حولك
and he has, you know, many adventures.
وسوف تواجه العديد من المغامرات
Some of those adventures are a little bit dark or on the darker side.
بعضها يحوي جوانب شريرة
Some of those adventures are wonderfully encouraging --
وبعضها محمسة بصورة مدهشة
he's got to go to school.
سوف يذهب الى المدرسة
The cool thing is
والشئ الرائع
that we're doing as well:
الذي قمنا به أيضاً:
as you interact with him,
بحسب تواصلك معه
you're able to put things into his world; he recognizes objects.
سوف تكون قادرا على اضافة اشياء الى عالمه .. وسوف يتعرف على الامور من حوله
His mind is based in a cloud.
ودماغه في الحقيقة هو كغيمة في السماء
That means Milo's mind,
اي ان دماغ مايلو .. وباستخدام
as millions of people use it,
الملاين له
will get smarter and cleverer.
سوف يصبح اكثر ذكاءُ وحنكةُ
He'll recognize more objects
وسوف يتعرف على العديد من الاشياء
and thus understand more words.
وسوف يتعرف على العديد من الكلمات
But for me,
وبالنسبة لي
this is a wonderful opportunity
انها فرصة رائعة
where technology, at last, can be connected with,
حيث يمكن للتكنولوجيا اليوم ان تتواصل معي
where I am no longer restrained
بدون اي قيود تفرض علي
by the finger I hold in my hand --
ولا على يدي .. ولا على اصابعي
as far as a computer game's concerned --
وهي لعبة غنية ليست كباقي الالعاب
or by the blandness of not being noticed
يمكن كشف نهايتها او حبكتها
if you're watching a film or a book.
كما يمكن كشف حبكة فلم او كتاب
And I love those revolutions,
بالنسبة لي هذه ثورة .. وانا احب الثورات
and I love the future that Milo brings.
وانا متحمس جدا للمستقبل الذي سيجلبه مايلو لنا
Thank you very much indeed.
شكراً جزيلا لكم !
(Applause)
(تصفيق)